yep
all right thanks daniel for having me
everyone at the active inference lab uh
sorry for canceling twice
uh life's been kind of crazy with uh
finishing uh this book that this talk
will be
about and having a kid i'm six months
old and i i got sick like a week ago
like right
leading up to like you know didn't want
to cancel a third time and look crazy so
this is a very rushed presentation
um it'll be better if it's more of like
a conversation since i haven't even gone
through the slides myself once um
and it's gonna get into a lot of things
like immediately like open up bags of
worms like there's just philosophical
issues
um
things that people won't agree about
like immediately but um
yeah so this is just going to be like a
small introduction
to the thesis in the book um and yeah
i'll explain more i guess uh after i
begin
so yeah it's uh
call this the integrated evolutionary
synthesis
um compared to like the modern synthesis
or even the extended evolutionary
synthesis this is integrated because it
uh
kind of reconceptualizes evolution
uh biology and evolution in terms of the
in terms of thermodynamics and
information theory or energy flows
energy and information flows um takes
from cybernetics
so
yeah it's a non-reductive theory of
everything
that includes emergent phenomena like
life mind and civilization
um i say that because most theories of
everything we're used to are fundamental
physics theories that don't have
anything to say about life and
consciousness
they ignore them um
and uh i don't think those should be
called theories of everything because
theories of everything should be
uh an explanation for everything and if
you leave the things that we care about
most out then
it's not much of a theory of everything
so this is the book i've spent the last
two to three years riding obsessively
and uh it's available for pre-order now
so if you want to check that out
um you can find it with a google search
uh here's the table of contents
um so the book is broken into three
sections uh part one uh talks about the
origins of life and part two
about evolution while part three focuses
on
uh
consciousness and free will and the fate
of life in the universe so these like
really big questions but we're gonna
focus on
part two
and uh give a pretty
like a superficial overview of part two
um but you can feel free to ask me
uh any questions about
uh any of the other topics that are
related and i'll try to see what i can
answer without going into like all of
the
information i would i would need to
explain those things um so thomas huxley
known as darwin's bulldog
because he was such a strong advocate
for darwin's theory said that the
question of questions for mankind the
problem which underlies all others is
more deeply interesting than any other
is the ascertainment and of the place
which man occupies in nature and of his
relations to the universe of things so
where do we fit into the grand cosmic
scheme
um most scientists in the 20th century
and i would even say
now um
believe uh that we are an accident so uh
jacques mano
french
biochemist who won the nobel prize for
uh physiology and medicine um wrote a
book called chance of necessity which
was really influential and
he was just as reductionist as you can
get man at last knows that he is alone
in the unfeeling immensity of the
universe out of which he emerged only by
chance
neither so some of the words are covered
by uh by daniel so neither is his
destiny spelled out or his duty have
been written down i think there's
something wrong with that quote but um
so if there are times where i'm trying
to read something where the picture's
over i might have to skip you can
you can move that because
it looks on my side it
it looks fine perfect thank you great
yeah um neither his destiny or his duty
have been written down
so that was kind of based on this old
idea that
uh
the emergence of life uh was a product
of chance assembly so like this uh just
a
statistical fluctuation
that brought together all the molecules
needed to create the first cell
we now know that that's probably not
what happened it's this gradual process
of self-organization jeremy england has
uh been in the media a lot about his
theory of dissipative adaptation
so um
let's
so we will see uh this is kind of like a
different point of view not everybody
was convinced by a mono uh carl sagan
said the origin of life must be a highly
probable affair as soon as conditions
permit
up it pops
um so this is an important question um
whether life was uh improbable or
inevitable so if life is highly
improbable we're likely to be alone in
the universe but if the emergence of
life is inevitable given a certain set
of common uh physical conditions then
it's likely that we have life
um at least on planets that are
sufficiently earth-like uh specifically
have
uh geochemistry like earth's uh uh have
a
star
uh some
uh like the earth's because that's what
uh provides the energy that pushes it
far from equilibrium so we're going to
get in to all that stuff pretty soon um
christian to do
this quote is kind of a
response to stephen j gould who just
really emphasized uh to both mono and
stephen jay gould
the
the importance of chance uh in nature
and that everything is basically
you know a contingency that came from a
chance process
um where did says that you know you can
have this inevitability that some
philosophers would see as as teleology
but it doesn't mean that uh this
inevitable progress is being driven by
the supernatural force he explains that
the natural constraints within which
chance operates are such that evolution
in the direction of increasing
complexity was virtually bound to take
place if given the opportunity chance
does not exclude inevitability so he was
also a nobel prize winning uh biologist
the same
category as mono but had a complete
opposite opinion
and we can talk about that too basically
uh
when uh systems are open systems and
they're pushed far from equilibrium
by a flow of energy you basically uh get
something like
a statistical bias away from what we
would expect with isolated systems
closed systems that aren't uh open to
energy will relax the thermodynamic
equilibrium
and
when a system is being pushed far from
equilibrium uh it will naturally
organize because uh organization
uh
happens uh under the flow of energy and
we're gonna see exactly why it's a
darwinian process
but
basically um
you get inevitability if you have the
right ingredients
so
um
we'll talk about to kind of frame this
we already kind of mentioned those two
world views so the first world view
would be the reductionist world view and
i should be clear that um productionism
is uh
also it's it's a method and an ideology
and we shouldn't uh confuse those two
things
um and daniel i guess just so i'm
you know know where i'm at maybe when
you when i've gone 30 minutes you can
let me know
okay i'll hoot
okay great um so
uh reductionism the method uh basically
says that reality can be understood by
breaking down all physical phenomena
into their simplest parts so that we may
observe the basic behavior of the
fundamental constituents of nature so
um
i'm just going to
plug in this charger i might need to do
that
a little bit but um basically uh the
method is how science works if we want
to understand emergence we also have to
understand how the components that
systems are made of uh work in isolation
so
it's an essential part of the story but
it's not the whole part we'll see um so
the method inspired an ideology and
ideology is is is just that it's it's an
ideology and it's rigid
and um
basically uh the method uh doesn't
really
um
imply that the ideology is true so um
when i'm attacking reductionism i'm not
attacking the method i'm i'm attacking
the worldview and so that view we can
say that um
basically um
so
hard determinism is is part of the
reductionist worldview
so uh
thought experiment that some people are
familiar with i'm sure la place is demon
but basically uh laplace was a
french mathematician that
uh took uh
newton's kind of model of reality uh and
applied it to everything newton himself
was kind of a mystic when it comes to
life he didn't really think that physics
applied to
to organisms or at least to humans but
um
laplace really you know
came up with the idea that like uh
basically the evolution of the universe
is just this like
um
clockwork universe where it's like um
a machine with cogs that are just
turning so there are no uh there's no
room for agency and free will in that
picture
when boltzmann came along uh in the 19th
century and
uh
came up with statistical mechanics
the clockwork universe kind of became
the billiard ball universe but it's just
the idea that
everything in the universe is made of
atoms and that these atoms are um
interacting and that's the whole picture
so the ideology says we're nothing more
than our atoms so we don't make
decisions
uh consciousness is just
an epic phenomenon and it
feels to us like we are but actually
this trajectory was determined basically
uh not basically from the moment of the
big bang
and there's kind of no freedom in
anything and uh no future
um
other than what was determined from the
beginning
so
the second law of thermodynamics also
sort of shaped the reduction of soil
abuse as the
universe is becoming increasingly
disordered there's actually kind of two
different interpretations of the second
law uh the first one
uh
kind of emerged from the work of uh
carnell and clausius the kind of
original thermodynamics work where
entropy was about
um a measure of uh
energy that can't be used for work so a
kind of measure of like useless
energy um
where later with boltzmann he tried to
uh
put the second law on like a statistical
basis based on like atomic theory so
um
basically uh
people applied uh boltzmann's
statistical interpretation of the second
law
to the universe and came up with this
notion that the universe is becoming
increasingly disordered which isn't
great for life because it means that
life is transient and likely cosmically
insignificant
and this worldview is associated with
materialism
uh which doesn't recognize consciousness
is real certainly doesn't recognize it
as having causal power
and historically it often ignored
apparently a material phenomenon like
energy and information and mental
processes
um
i am just going to
grab my charger so
um
sounds good this doesn't die but i will
be right back take your time
so
those who are watching live please feel
free to leave a
comment or a question i'm writing some
things down
we'll look forward to the return of
electrical power to bobby
all right
my first live stream i will be more
prepared when i return
to part two that's something else i've
told daniel is that this is kind of like
part one and i like to come back and
talk about
uh
the ideas that come after
so
it will have 15.2 it'll be awesome it's
an infinite sequence it's the sequence
is always yours
great
okay um so
reductionist worldview says that all
life forms including humans are nothing
more than collections of atoms
obligatory following fixed and arbitrary
mechanical trajectories determined
solely by math and not by mine
so
um
this world view if
if you convince someone that they don't
have free will because you tell them
about the
reductionist worldview um there was
actually a study where they did this and
they
read participants a passage from francis
crick explaining
that uh it appears that we don't have
any free will
um the participants
actually on subsequent tests
uh were more like more likely to cheat
on the test
because they felt like they didn't have
any personal responsibility they weren't
making the decisions therefore they
could cheat that's kind of funny because
they are actually you can see that like
by what they're like being told they are
changing
uh their behavior so it is having some
kind of effect if we do in fact have an
agency or free will and we're kind of
talking about agency uh we don't really
get into free will but those are related
topics but if that's not true
then uh that's really bad that the
majority of scientists are telling
people we don't have free will because
the people that believe this
um
it's having negative effects on for
example mental health other studies have
shown that belief and no free will can
lead to depression and belief in free
will can have all these
positive effects um
of course soon as i start talking about
free will
i'm sure a lot of people
have objections uh might think that
there's no way that we can have room for
free will in a physical world view um
but that's exactly what we're going to
begin to talk about today uh the causal
power of information
and that basically organisms are agents
that are
cybernetic control units so
as controllers
we do have agency
so
and the belief that were accidents of
nature rather than natural
manifestations of
physical laws uh i'm sure also
uh impacts our sense
of well-being just so you know i'm not
making this up um i can i'll give you
some
quotes from really famous physicists
who are uh kind of militant reductionist
so
brian green says i think it's very
important to face up to the truth of
reality which is in fact that life and
consciousness
is a fleeting phenomenon on the entire
cosmological timeline
um
brian green just came out with a book
and he's like going on interviews just
saying this and it's really interesting
because some other famous physicists
don't agree at all and he's stating it
like it's a complete fact so for example
david deutsch would not agree with this
and we'll get into that um sabine
hostenfelder is another person um
i know some of the
some of my friends in the community um
who are
these people you know working on
emergence and causation and stuff uh get
bothered by her statements because she's
also very
uh ultra reductionistic so i wish people
would stop insisting they have free will
it's terribly annoying insisting that
free will exist as bad science like
insisting that horoscopes tell you
something about the future it's not
compatible with our knowledge about
nature so uh
i'm saying that's wrong we won't get
into free will that much but if you have
questions at the end we will
talk about how information adaptive
information
uh gets built up by evolution in uh
adaptive systems complex adaptive
systems and you will see how uh these
systems actually do control their own
future
so sam harris is another anti-freewheel
person says you're not controlling the
storm and you are not lost in it you are
the storm so it's kind of funny because
he's using a metaphor here but what this
story kind of reveals
is that uh
yes we are a storm that's right we are a
dissipative structure like a storm uh
emerges to dissipate uh an energy
gradient
and uh we're not really gonna talk about
that that's what the first part of the
book is about the origins part but um
i'm just pointing it out because it's
interesting because we are like a storm
in that aspect but we also differ from a
storm because a storm does not have
agency a storm does not have the ability
to seek out new energy gradients it's
just kind of
um
being pushed around by these gradients
in nature where uh
organisms are actually controllers and
so you are storm
but you do have control over the storm
so
uh
these people are kind of
have the opposite view so julio tinoni
uh creator of integrated information
theory says there is true free will
a great lecture that just popped up i
think months ago where he gives a
two-hour talk on
uh basically integrate information and
uh how it shows that
systems do have causal power and uh
in a way uh have free will so
depending on your definition of free
will
um
we do have free will according to his
model
david deutsch said in an interview with
john horgan just uh a year ago or so i'm
sure we have free will
christoph koch says explains how you
know there are a lot of experiments the
lebet experiments
which we will talk about next time
that uh
basically yeah some people interpret it
as as not having free will but actually
uh we will see later um
when you deliberate
uh that's actually an act of free will
these choices were actually where you
bring your entire conscious being to
that question and try to analyze it
under all the various conditions and
actually uh there was a study coke did
that kind of
showed that the lebate lebet study uh
um was kind of interpreted wrong and um
for anyone
who understands that stuff uh the
readiness potential that was supposed to
be
proof that there was no free will
disappeared when the decisions uh
involved uh deliberation so yeah that's
kind of
meandering but i'm sure a lot of people
are interested in this bigger picture of
why this emergence
paradigm is so radically different from
the reductionist paradigm it kind of uh
puts information front and center and
systems that process information
uh complex adaptive systems are
computational systems
and these systems uh
in the with these systems information
actually does have causal power we're
gonna explain what we mean by that so
paradigm of emergence uh
the collective says the collective
behavior of interacting parts not simply
how they function in isolation is key to
understanding the emergence and
evolution
of all the fascinating organisms and
ecosystems that make up the biosphere so
it's really not about
just like particles it's about the
patterns that emerge when uh these
systems find these certain
configurations uh through basically
darwinian mechanisms and we'll see that
self-organization too uh has a darwinian
dynamic
each emergence in the cosmic
self-organization process is brought
about by higher order phase transition
that moves life ever further away from a
state of thermodynamic equilibrium and
total disorder
i'm assuming the audience knows uh that
what thermodynamic equilibrium is it's
basically
uh if you have for example boltzmann
took a model of um
an ideal gas and explained that for
example if the gas molecules are bunched
up in the corner uh naturally it's going
the gas is going to spread out until
there's no pattern and uh basically it's
like a completely mixed up state um
so equilibrium is associated with death
and disorder uh because systems
naturally tend toward this more
mixed up
unpatterned
completely chaotic state
of course
later we're gonna talk about uh why open
systems that that rule doesn't apply
basically systems that are open to the
flow of energy can resist this tendency
towards a disorder and that's really
what the whole story is kind of
based on um
so through a nested series of such phase
transitions these are also called
these higher order phase transitions are
major evolutionary transitions john
maynard smith talked about them and meta
system transitions by the cyberneticist
valentine terchin basically the same
concept of some subtle differences
so the idea is that cosmic
self-organization is a series of these
transitions where functional things come
together to make larger functional ones
which come together to even
make even larger ones and so on and
through this process adaptive complexity
or life so that's a more general way to
talk about life
becomes better equipped to dominate the
cosmos life requires an organization
that is increasingly hierarchical and
integrated and therefore more resilient
and computationally powerful
so
here are just a couple of figures
you see this hierarchy uh in this
structural hierarchy of matter in life
this was adapted from
a big physics journal i can't remember
which one it was but um
basically you know physicists are
recognizing
this hierarchy even when it extends to
life so jeffrey west's book scale comes
to mind
and so we see the
hierarchy of science kind of naturally
mirror this hierarchy
of matter and life
and um the reductionist picture would
say that these things at the top here
um
are kind of insignificant
parts of the story transient but we will
see that this
you know the more we go up the more
influence
on cosmic evolution the phenomena have
so
uh thomas huxley's question about a
man's place in the cosmos uh
is um
basically the emergence of paradigm uh
the paradigm of emergence i'm going to
discuss and actually this is kind of
maybe like in a specific or a new
paradigm of emergence because it
includes all this stuff about
thermodynamics and information theory um
says that emergence the emergence and
evolution of life mind societies and
technology are all part of one
thermodynamic process one evolutionary
process one computational process
unified by the concept of knowledge
so
uh this theory is a theory of knowledge
creation
and so knowledge is going to be the
unifying theme and we'll briefly talk
about epistemology i wanted to talk
about it more but it just would have
been too long um cosmic evolution
uh in this paradigm is a universal
process of becoming as opposed to being
so the universe isn't this static thing
uh it's actually evolving
very much like an organism or a complex
adaptive system
um so it's not a pan psychic theory in
this theory consciousness emerges that's
very important um but you might call it
emergent pan-psychism uh because
uh as this evolutionary process proceeds
uh inanimate matter as life spreads gets
converted into animate matter
um so in this picture humans are neither
a cosmic accident nor the end goal of
evolution
so we are instead a step on the
evolutionary ladder of becoming
and we are also potentially an essential
driver of increasing cosmic complexity
so this big idea is that the universe is
undergoing this majestic self-organizing
process and at this moment of time at
least in this corner of the universe we
are the stars of the show
um this picture is from eric chasen's uh
book the rise of complexity uh cosmic
evolution the rise of complexity
he's a harvard astrophysicist
but i just used freeman dyson code here
because it seemed relevant
it's conceivable that life may have a
larger role to play than we have yet
imagined life may succeed against all
odds and molding the universe to its own
purpose
so i guess brian green doesn't buy that
at all but um
if that's true then uh
as phys as cosmology cosmologists have
to think about the
role of life there's a lot of people
who've said similar things like seth
lloyd and
famously raker as well um
so
just a couple quotes here so you know
you know when when people hear these
terms progress there's just the stigma
immediately they thought like oh
someone's trying to sneak in religion or
some intelligent design theory
so you see these trusted names
of physics here david deutsch has
narrowly conceived evolutionary theory
considers as mere vehicles for the
replication of our genes our memes and
it refuses to address the question of
why evolution has tended to create ever
greater adaptive complexity or the role
that such complexity plays in the wider
scheme of things so
there is clearly implying that adaptive
complexity does have this larger role to
play
we now see how it is possible for the
universe to increase both organization
and entropy at the same time the
optimistic and pessimistic arrows of
time can coexist the universe can
display creative unidirectional
unidirectional progress even in the face
of the second law because this is paul
davies says that
um so that's really uh
kind of a key point
uh in this is that um
the second law actually is in a sense
driving this increasing progress so not
only can we have unidirectional progress
in the face of the second law it seems
that this progress requires the second
law
because we'll see that the second law is
the
basically the natural selection pressure
for uh self-organizing systems so in a
sense the second law is both uh shiva
the destroyer and brahma the creator um
so
a goal of this unifying theory of
reality
uh
i've been calling the great consilience
it was actually a name
uh suggested by marco lin
who is uh
is a fristonian in influenced uh some of
this talk
um so
basically the unifying theory of reality
illuminates the connection between
complexity cognition consciousness and
cosmic evolution or matter mind and
cosmos
um and it's really based on complexity
science it's a lot broader than
complexity science but i guess that
name kind of
in a way includes everything so it's a
unification of major sciences of our
time including but not limited to
physics biology neuroscience computer
science evolutionary theory and
statistics
and basically it describes complex
adaptive systems of all scales in terms
of energy and information flows
so
it uses statistical thermodynamics
information theory and cybernetics um so
we will talk about those a bit
uh coming up so if you want to see kind
of like a
a map of what sort of informs uh
this non-reductive theory of everything
here you go so
i know there's a lot of information so
i'll kind of try to simplify this for
everyone
um there are some unifying paradigms
that have emerged so basically this
theory is nothing new it's basically
evolutionary epistemology
um after that came universal darwinism
and later uh right now we're seeing this
kind of revolution with like bayesian
inference and these ideas being applied
to everything
um so
uh
being informed uh by these
um
paradigms
and
uh combining those paradigms are
updating them i should say with uh
information from non-equilibrium
thermodynamics so we're talking about
the thermodynamics of open systems
uh information theory so shannon's
theory
some of you will know that information
theory is related very closely to
non-equilibrium thermodynamics and
basically uh boltzmann's statistical
entropy is mathematically the same as
shannon entropy or information entropy
which is a measure of uncertainty um
if i had more time i would go through
thermodynamics and the different types
of entropy but
we don't have time for that but if
anyone has any questions i can clarify
um cybernetics was
basically information theory
applied to biology adaptive systems it
was the first
science of adaptive systems really and
uh it's funny while writing this uh i
found out because you know i hadn't
i had heard the name cybernetics but it
wasn't clear how important it was
um
in a talk by uh jim crutchfeld uh santa
fe institute basically
revealed that uh because cybernetics got
associated with like the russian
uh like during the cold war kind of like
the russian agenda um cybernetics was
used to design like heat-seeking
missiles uh norbert weiner's
theory was almost immediately applied
for military uses and because of that it
stopped being taught in american
colleges
so
yeah it's really important and it was
actually
emerging at the same time as information
theory people were already uh thinking
about
systems in terms of information flows
but it's more than information theory
because it's a science of feedback
um
so dynamical systems theory or complex
adaptive systems is kind of like an
offshoot of that all of these inform
what i've called universal basianism not
the only person to call it that
i had searched that term and found adam
saffron's uh paper on integrated world
modeling theory that used that same term
but uh john campbell has been a
researcher
um
who has done a lot to show this
equivalence between
uh
evolutionary processes and processes of
bayesian inference we're going to talk
about that in a little bit um
so yeah if anybody has any questions
about that but really all of these
things origin of life research
integrated evolutionary theory um
if you haven't checked out the work of
these people like everybody here is
worth reading their work but uh so from
that we get a unifying theory of reality
that is based on
what i call the evolutionary
epistemology universal darwinism
universal bayesianism framework that's a
long name i'm aware of that but it's
just to show that these three theories
are basically the same theory
so
universal darwinism says that the
universe is evolving at every scale
through both competitive evolution and
through self-organization which is
cooperative evolution among agents that
have formed a collective unit
so it started with richard dawkins and
this concept of the meme and the selfish
gene that
uh memes uh were these uh cultural units
that were equivalent to genes
and so we started to see how information
was this
uh paradigm that
could be extended beyond biology and
then we had dan dinnett and darwin's
dangerous idea really extend this to
like everything to
self-organizing systems to cultural and
technological systems
uh evolutionary cosmology came before
that it was based on karl popper's
philosophy but it was actually invented
by cognitive psychologist donald
campbell
and basically that said that the
evolutionary process
is a problem-solving procedure that
creates knowledge so
uh
the information stored in genomes and in
uh brains and cultural memory uh
basically
that all that knowledge accumulates from
an evolutionary process and
it's really helpful to think of it as
knowledge especially when we start to
talk about this
in in uh the context of thermodynamics
and information because uh basically
this knowledge is what allows
life adaptive systems
to stay far from equilibrium they can
resist this tendency towards decay
life can uh continue to persist
if it can acquire
the knowledge that it needs
to essentially to find free energy
that will allow it to sustain itself um
so we'll talk about that in a second
more
um so universal bayesianism is a
bayesian update of the first two
paradigms knowledge is encoded so the
knowledge that evolutionary epistemology
can describe
it's actually encoded in biological
systems
uh in the form of a world model
so this model is an internal
representation and statistical mapping
of the environment which gets updated
through adaptation and adaptive learning
we're going to talk about that process
um
really the
the whole
bayesian brain hypothesis and free
energy principle is inspired by
cybernetics heavily so ross ashby's
good regulator theorem and law of
requisite variety which we'll talk about
was kind of the first talk of
systems having models and having to
model the environment um so kaufristen
says inference is actually quite close
to a theory of everything including
evolution consciousness and life itself
we're not going to go into
those bigger implications that
would be at the
end of the book in the last chapter but
basically this isn't just a theory about
evolution
um well it is evolution but evolution
applied way more broadly so quantum
mechanics has a an interpretation that's
consistent with this and bigger problems
like the fine-tuning of the constants
and parameters that allow for the
emergence
of life in the universe we can actually
uh probably have the best explanation
for the fine-tuning problem and the
measurement problem of quantum mechanics
uh with this theory um
we won't talk about it but just so you
know next time uh cosmological natural
selection by lee smolin is the theory
that kind of addresses the fine-tuning
problem from a universal darwinism
perspective
while quantum darwinism
uh addresses the measurement problem
um so we will save that for next time
but feel free to ask questions about any
of those so
what does this do i have this name
poetic meta naturalism i meant to take
that out but uh next time we'll get into
why
uh i chose that name it's actually um it
sounds kind of like you know like
complex or buzzword or jargony but
there's actually very practical reasons
for having that name um
so this uh unifying theory bridges
matter with mine so universal darwinism
gives us a picture of the open-ended
complexity growth
uh
that this whole idea is based on the
idea that evolution
keeps producing increasingly complex
intelligent forms of life
excuse me
um
so uh
yeah universal bayesianism is uh the
link that kind of connects those
paradigms with
uh consciousness so again we won't get
into that today but
when uh you understand that knowledge is
stored stored in the form of a world
model that a system that models itself
can experience then we start to
get a better understanding of like what
conscious consciousness
consciousness is it's a it's a mental
model so it's not a traditional pan
psychic theory even though i know
firsthand and
levin and some of his colleagues have
kind of been flirting with fan psychism
this
theory would say that's wrong and it's
kind of uh
reduces consciousness to something
trivial um by saying that it's in
everything like
a proton is conscious because it's a
triad of corks that have to be in a
certain configuration so there is some
minimal level of integrated information
um that's not enough uh
to get a conscious experience again
observer um so saffron's integrated
world modern theory says that you need a
model with spatial temporal and causal
coherence
i would also argue that it requires
self-modeling capacity
talk about that a little bit at the end
if anyone's interested but this theory
is supposed to bridge mine with cosmic
evolution
so the story starts
with the second law um
daniel if there's any questions about
that like intro let me know
yeah i can just proceed could i ask two
questions from the chat
sure okay the first question is from
blue blue wrote
do you think that non-living autonomous
agents with multiple competing
priorities such as self-driving cars
have free will
if not what is the defining difference
between these systems and humans
uh no i don't think they have free will
so um adaptive information is a special
type of information i do think
those things and this is kind of
following sarah walker's lead
who's at arizona state and she's also
sfi faculty now but
basically um
to have self-driving cars you first need
life
so
anything like a self-driving car that's
like this information processing system
uh if you
were to come across a
broken down self-driving car
on some planet and you saw that you
would have to infer that there was also
life there because life is part of the
trajectory to get to that
but i wouldn't say that it has free will
because it's just this input output
machine uh with a defined set of
algorithms
and
adaptive systems
are more flexible uh and
there
okay so in the next
next time we'll talk about
actually the emergence of agency
which occurs with the origin apply for
abiogenesis
and you basically um
because this self-organized system that
would be kind of like the protocell
is evolving through a mechanism that a
darwinian dynamic for self-organization
that will explain in a bit it builds up
information and at some point there's a
phase transition or the information
that's getting built up in the system uh
basically uh gains
what sarah walker and paul davies call
informational control so there's a point
where information actually starts
calling the shots
and
you can see the difference
between uh
systems that where there is
informational control uh so living
systems and inanimate systems because
for example
um
inanimate systems uh their movement can
be predicted with newton's laws so
anyone who's taken first year physics uh
probably had to do an exercise where
you're trying to predict the movement of
some
macroscopic system like a ball that gets
kicked or pushed by
a gust of wind and what you do is
you um
you have to draw out all the forces
acting on the system and then you can
understand where the system is going to
go
with life you don't need an external
force for it to start for example
climbing up hill um that's internally
generated of course it's not magic
the adaptive system the agent
has stored energy that it's extracted
from the environment so for example
humans that have eaten food and there's
a metabolic process that's driving this
but
uh still yeah you with living systems
that where information has causal power
basically the trajectory of the system
can't be predicted
by these fundamental laws of physics
philip ball a journalist that
has been talking about this
his recent article which caused a lot of
controversy between like
the reductionists like talking about
free will and agency um and there's a
lot of confusion around that so people
like jerry coyne were like trying to
shoot it down and
yeah hopefully i can talk about that um
i guess we'll talk about that next time
because there's a lot of
uh confusion
about what we're saying when we say
something has agency or free will but
his example is if you throw throw a ball
and a bird off a tower
and
you can predict
what one is going to do you can't
predict what the other is going to do
interestingly though i would say that
the bird's not completely unpredictable
you can predict that it's not going to
hit the ground it's not going to splat
on the ground
it's going to fly away you have to
understand the bird in terms of its
goals so you have to understand
you know the bird and its environment
and the information that got built up
through evolution
and then we can start to predict the
bird uh its statistical behavior so
inanimate systems you can pretty much
precisely predict the movement
unless they're chaotic systems which is
another story but with life um
yeah it's not predictable in that same
way with like low-level
laws of physics but uh i'm arguing that
actually life is more predictable than
we thought
but you need things like
non-equilibrium statistical mechanics
and
for example uh
free energy principle um
so you can say that you know an organism
will
try to minimize free energy or
minimize the difference between uh its
model's
prediction and reality so it will try to
minimize prediction error and that's
a way that we can start to describe uh
behavior statistically
um
yo is there another one yep can i ask
the second question
yeah i i know i didn't completely
answer that but uh that will require
like the all the points that i would get
into in the second talk but it's a great
question yeah i would have written in a
larger margin if i had more time
the second question is from joseph clark
who wrote
uh first complimented your talk and let
you knew that you were an interesting
guy
so then the question was
how far
do you think the universe can organize
itself and what does that look like
okay great that's a perfect question to
lead into the next part and hopefully by
the end of this
we will have some sort of answer for
that
which is good because i when i started
making the beginning of the presentation
i was going to get to consciousness and
free will and i ran out of time so
there's been a lot of talk about things
that i won't get to but that we will get
to
um so
the story starts with the second law um
so the second law of thermodynamics has
popularly popularly understood says that
uh systems naturally become increasingly
disordered
um that's really just because of the
large-scale effects of chance so
there are many ways to be disordered and
there are relatively fewer ways to be
patterned
so
a system that's this
collective of particles so this evolving
ensemble of particles
will naturally tend to move towards a
configuration that's completely spread
out and mixed up there are no
uh
energy gradients so no work can be
extracted that's a state of equilibrium
so we are going to use this word
thermodynamic equilibrium
to mean death and disorder so life wants
to resist the tendency towards
equilibrium it wants to stay ordered
uh what's interesting about this is that
it applies to all this is kind of like
where
the free energy principle and for
instance bayesian brain hypothesis it
frames everything this way so i thought
it was
a good way to kind of frame it here is
that you start with the second law and
any conceivable system any ordered
system for it to continue to persist has
to resist this uh tendency
so
um
basically
uh schroedinger the guy everybody knows
from quantum mechanics in the in the cat
thought experiment he wrote a book
called what is life in the 40s and
basically kind of solved his paradox
like if there's a second law and things
become more disordered than what's with
life and what's with the biosphere and
all this complexity that we see around
us
and he explained actually boltzmann
explained this before him
um
bud boltzmann said a lot to contradict
this as well
um
or just didn't follow this to its
implications but uh schrodinger
explained that open systems uh by
feeding off uh free energy in the
environment so free energy is just
energy that uh you can extract work from
so it's ordered energy as opposed to
energy that's been dissipated in the
form of heat you can't extract energy uh
uh useful energy from that energy it's
still there it's just spread out and
it's it's you can't harness it
collecting it would cost more than you'd
get out of it so um
schrodinger explained that uh if a
system can get free energy which he
called negative entropy
or energy uh neg entropies was called by
uh someone later
so to understand
how ordered systems stay ordered
uh
you basically need to understand that
they have to
constantly be extracting free energy
from the environment
the moment that they can't
extract more free energy is the moment
that the system dies and decays to
equilibrium so
basically uh the second law is not
violated by life because
um
in this effort to stay far from
equilibrium life it keeps extracting
that ordered free energy and keeps
dissipating it as heat
so and so it's basically exporting
entropy
into the environment so the order
um
that is maintained
is paid for
by
the dissipated energy which come becomes
thermal entropy so there are multiple
definitions of entropy so you have
thermal entropy which is heat entropy
and then statistical entropy
which explains thermal entropy but it
has a broader domain of application so
you can talk about
shuffling a deck of cards
and you can talk about like the
statistical entropy increasing
if the deck is ordered and it starts
becoming mixed up through the shuffling
but the deck of cards the thermal
entropy uh isn't changing much at all so
there's different types of entropy
there's also information entropy which
has to do with the um
uh the number of messages that could be
sent across the channel
instead of um
the number of states that a system can
be in the number of microstates without
changing the macro state macro state or
the kind of
collective properties of the system
there's a really neat
relationship between statistical entropy
and information entropy
which i won't talk about here it was
really fleshed out by
e.t janes
but yeah so
information and entropy like go hand in
hand
um just to
give a little more context before we get
into the details uh david deutsch and
this great ted talk
um called after billions of years of
monotony the universe is waking up says
if one can speak of a cosmic war it's a
war between monotony and novelty between
stasis and creativity and in this war
our side is not destined to lose if we
choose to apply our unique capacity to
create explanatory knowledge we could
win
so that's very different than brian
green's story and it kind of gets at the
second question that was asked there how
how far can this complexity increase go
and so this kind of foreshadows that
maybe it doesn't have a limit
and that seems you know most people
think that would go against the second
half of their own dynamics we're going
to see why that's not necessarily true
but you can also see this cosmic war as
this fight between order versus disorder
life versus entropy
and knowledge versus uncertainty or
ignorance
um but
is life's battle against disorder uh
good versus evil or yin and yang so i'm
gonna kind of argue that these two
things kind of
have this uh
you could describe their relationship as
causally
dependent and it's kind of like this
dialectic between
life and
uh disorder um
and it is through this
sort of uh interaction
that uh creates progress so we have some
eastern ideas mentioned again um but i
when i was writing the book a friend
that
practices buddhism called me and told me
about this interdependent colorizing
idea which i thought was really cool so
we're going to come up with this what we
call poppers principle which is
problems create progress we're going to
see that this problem
of entropy that this tendency towards
decay
is what actually
forces systems
to evolve basically it forces them to
search
what's called the configuration space
for the phase space for the state space
to find configurations that are good at
extracting energy and
that allows it to stay far from
equilibrium
so we're going to have some figures soon
so this stuff that's kind of abstract
becomes a little bit more concrete
just
out of respect to the earlier request
how about you check the time
and feel then how fast you'd like to
continue however much you want to
present and then if you want to take any
questions but first just
check the time and let
just i i
i didn't uh
i didn't
notice when we started so about how long
have i been going i would say five zero
minutes
really
okay how long can we go
we can go another
uh 99 minutes okay
um i'll try to go through it a little
bit faster um
but yeah so um
but if we use all the time i told you
yesterday that i was feeling uh oh i had
a sore throat and uh the sore throat's
better today i'm hopped up on cold
medicine i'm sure i'm gonna
i'm gonna pay for tomorrow but um
yeah if we use all the time with
questions that would be good uh so
in our everyday experiment experience
things don't
naturally
become ordered unless someone intervenes
rooms get messier buildings erode
uh so we already talked about this
schrodinger's
solution so we can think of life as a
game
so life has always been playing a game
against the second law of thermodynamics
there is another narrative that i won't
go into but life is also an energy flow
channel so life
by existing in computing and trying to
stay far from equilibrium
is also increasing entropy uh actually
the universe of life will increase
entropy at a faster rate than a universe
without life
um which is pretty interesting so it's
again not necessarily that life is like
battling against entropy in in many ways
it increases entropy but
there's also this story i guess what
it's trying to battle is a tendency
towards disorder so it depends on what
type of entropy you're talking about
um
so the challenge in the game of life
which applies to you as well as other
simpler adaptive systems is to resist
that tendency so this gives life a goal
or a tediology so two algae was
associated with kind of this mystical
thing but
basically we'll we're seeing that
tediology is just uh agency it's just a
result
goal-oriented behavior as a result of
the information that's been
accumulated over evolution so teleology
the book uh tries to naturalize the
theology and just say that they're these
goal-oriented systems that behave
different
uh because
they are acquiring information through
darwinian evolution
um
so life has to extract free energy
that's how it stays in the game of life
and to extract free energy it's it's not
a simple task so the computational task
of extracting free energy
uh requires that the uh system acquire
information about its environment
otherwise it can't find energy
uh it also requires that the system
model its environment so the information
is creating this predictive model this
generative model
and it is
um that model that allows it to
continuously
find free energy
um so we will explain that life strategy
is it searches through a configuration
space for solutions to the problem of
survival through trial and error search
uh variation and selection so we we know
about evolution there's this
genetic variation in natural selection
and uh we're going to argue that that
process that mechanism is much broader
the evolutionary mechanism is actually
the mechanism of the scientific method
and of adaptive learning um and that
mechanism is also a process that
accumulates evidence-based knowledge so
it's also a process
of bayesian inference we're going to
explain why so here we have those
different mechanisms with different
names
um
so it's not included here but uh so if
life is a game there are levels to this
game uh and the levels we're going to
see are these uh evolutionary
transitions every time life graduates to
this uh more
uh complex uh hierarchical system like
when
single-celled organisms come together to
form a multi-cellular organism and
multicellular organisms come together to
form
communities like societies uh that you
can
view these evolutionary transitions as
life graduating to a new level
so um
we're going to talk about how adaptive
information gets built up through
evolution and
we're calling that knowledge it's nice
to have that word knowledge because this
process of an adaptive system acquiring
this information is actually reducing
its uncertainty about the environment so
it's it's reducing its ignorance about
all the ways the surrounding world could
potentially surprise it
uh so knowledge is a nice word some
philosophers like old school
philosophers might have issue with that
um because in some
teachings like knowledge is something
that like conscious beings with like
awareness have but we're calling any
adaptive information knowledge and it's
got more of a technical definition
because knowledge is that information
which reduces
uh uncertainty and you could actually
quantify this process of evolution
terence deakin
has talked a lot about how you can do
that with uh information measures
um
so just to explain this why is knowledge
something that matters like does it have
causal power or is it all just this this
billiard ball universe where it's like
these particles bumping into each other
and you can basically use
uh fundamental laws of physics to
describe like the trajectory of all the
particles in the universe this is saying
no
that uh the information that gets built
up through evolution has causal power
such that these systems start to behave
in ways that are different than what
would be predicted from uh something our
newton's laws
so
we also have this process of
anti-accretion that sarah walker likes
to talk about uh but anti so
anti-accretion is
uh basically we're familiar with uh
planets pulling in matter so bodies like
asteroids because uh gravity pulls
matter in
naturally but anti-accretion is when a
planet is ejecting matter
and uh in many cases what
well so the the only time we really see
anti-accretion uh is when you have a
planet with life on it so
um
right now
uh bits of biosphere so humans and space
rockets are being sent to other
celestial bodies so that's a form of
anti-accretion uh sending up satellites
you won't see a satellite get sent out
if you see that in the universe like
you're looking at some other solar
system and you see
a body
uh sent out and put into orbit from a
planet that's an indication that life is
there that's a biosignature
so she says that
anti-christian requires comprehenders
specifically the existence of physical
systems with knowledge of newton's laws
um
so
what does it all mean
um it means we need knowledge uh to uh
keep us out of thermodynamic equilibrium
um
so
how do we acquire knowledge uh science
is the most
uh is the most salient example of the
causal power of knowledge so
science uh
has uh eradicated lethal diseases built
a global communication network called
the internet and created weapons of
apocalyptic power it's not always good
this power of knowledge but um
uh we see that there's something about
the scientific method
which is efficient at
uh accumulating
knowledge so we're going to talk about
why and that's where we get into karl
popper and evolutionary epistemology
um
so we know knowledge is important
karl popper says we're always faced with
practical problems and out of these grow
sometimes theoretical problems before we
try to solve some of our problems by
proposing theories
so uh
popper stresses that all of science
starts with a problem either theoretical
or practical
um and it is that problem that forces us
to seek out a solution so we can already
see why this
principle that called poppers principle
uh uh says that problems create progress
so
some of these theories that we make to
try to solve our problems will be wrong
they'll be errors
um but the idea with science is that
those errors get filtered out
by a process of testing your theories
and a peer review process which gives
criticism
so uh knowledge is really uh for
knowledge for us to know
that some piece of information is
knowledge
it really needs to be tested
and uh we call that evidence-based
knowledge or evidence-based information
so it's really the only true kind of
knowledge because you don't know if
something's true until you test it
for example um
the world doesn't look round from a
naive perspective it looks flat so for
example um
someone who had the first idea you know
and i'm sure it was before anybody
famous we knew someone had this idea and
probably people blew it off
but um
some things that are true about reality
are not immediate immediately apparent
from like sensory observation from since
data so we really need to test our
theories if we are going to be sure
about them um so what popper found out
was the scientific method is an
algorithm he called that algorithm
conjecture and refutation
and uh
basically this is the method of
hypothesis testing so you have a problem
you believe can be solved you make an
informed guess or conjecture to see if
your theory can be refuted uh prove
false by testing its predictions
so
uh people have pointed out like john
campbell
uh carl fristen that
science is a process of inference so it
recognizes statistical patterns and
trends in nature that we can use to make
increasingly accurate predictions
it would not be inaccurate then to say
that the functional purpose of science
is to generate predictive knowledge
and we can characterize that as process
of inference which basically means that
scientists draw logical conclusions
about the way the world works
uh based on evidence-based information
acquired in the past
but with never present awareness that
the information can and will lead to
um
to new conclusions and deeper
understanding so
when we recognize this we also have to
recognize that all of our models will
have uncertainty
so we should never think that our
model's right every model is going to be
proved wrong in some way but through the
scientific process uh the idea is that
we get closer and closer to truth so we
can never reach perfect truth but in
this model you can actually get closer
to it so in some senses it's different
than like post-modernist philosophy that
says there is no objective truth there
is an objective truth um
uh but we can never know it but we can
get closer to it
so
once popper understood that knowledge
the knowledge generating mechanism
behind science success was conjecture
and reputation he realized that human
learning which begins at birth and
continues to adapt uses the same
problem-solving algorithm
although the developmental psychology
literature called the method trial and
error
so because life is constantly presenting
us with new challenges such as the need
to get from one place to another a
problem that inspires babies to learn to
walk we must constantly try out new
behavioral solutions we can think of
these actions as guesses about how to
survive or if you prefer experiments in
evading equilibrium or predictions for
persistence
and they will often fail
um so
this is dan dinette's idea of life
exploring this design space we're going
to talk about how it does so through
evolution but we're still talking about
science here and adaptive learning on
abstract level we can imagine a certain
practical problem as a challenge one
with a solution that exists somewhere
out there in the space of possibilities
just waiting to be found by someone
sufficiently motivated and clever
it may take some time but if the
possibilities face the space of possible
solutions is continuously explored in an
efficient way
eventually a solution will be discovered
so excuse me trial and error learning
explores the solution space um
so
just to give you a
clear example of how adaptive learning
uh is kind of this form of hypothesis
testing so whenever we have a problem in
life and we don't know the correct
solution to a problem in advance
um we naturally begin with those
potential solutions that are closer to
our starting point in the solution space
for sampling so for example if a baby
reaches for its bottle and barely misses
it'll adjust its behavior slightly which
minimizes the chances of making an error
so
our instincts may nudge us in the
general direction of a solution but the
instinct alone is not enough
uh
we have to try out what you could call a
behavioral conjecture and when it fails
uh we
try something new so that's kind of like
a new theory
and it's essentially the old one but
with a little twist
and if that behavioral solution is
remembered then it gets stored for
future use ready to be repeated
but also adapted if necessary
um
but in humans so
the baby example reaching for the bottle
let's say it misses the bottle it won't
get a reward signal it won't get a
little surge of dopamine so if it
corrects and it gets closer it gets a
little reward signal this is
reinforcement learning but basically
this adaptive learning process is a
process of making theories and
eliminating those theories that are
errors
so
uh
popper saw that scientific knowledge
and the evolutionary process
were also connected so not only is
science
uh adaptive learning
uh both of those things are extensions
of the evolutionary process so he says
in science theories are highly
competitive we discuss them critically
we test them and we eliminate those
theories which we judge to be less good
in solving the problems which we wish to
solve so only the best theories those
which are most fit survive in the
struggle this is the way science grows
um so that's kind of nice like showing
you
really how this is an evolutionary
process
um not only is science an evolutionary
process the converse is true evolution
is a scientific process so
it is clear this is another quote it is
clear that this view of the progress of
science is very similar to darwin's view
of natural selection by the way of the
elimination of the unfit
of the errors in the evolution of life
the errors the attempts at adaptation
which is a trial and error process
analogously science works by trial
theory making and by the elimination of
heirs um
i might pause in a second just to
see if everybody understands this but i
have a few more slides so
um evolutionary algorithms uh also use
this mechanism but it's called generate
and test
so i didn't mention this uh the
mechanism of evolution is variation in
selection so
we have
these algorithms that are equivalent
conjecture and reputation trial and
error variation and selection we also
have generate and test so in machine
learning evolutionary algorithms
have this method
generating tests
possible solutions are generated into an
actual solution is found and these
solutions accumulate in some memory
store while the errors are filtered out
and forgotten
in science solutions our theories are
models that activate predicts the
natural phenomenon
and the successful ones accumulate in
peer-reviewed journals and textbooks
so
um
we see that these processes are
equivalent we're actually going to see
that it's this bayesian process
uh that adaptation
is also a process of
uh the model of the organism uh becoming
optimized uh decreasing its prediction
error so that can more efficiently
extract free energy from an itch to stay
ordered
so
we get this principle um that all
evolutionary processes are learning
processes and all learning processes are
evolutionary processes
conrad lawrence a nobel prize-winning
zoologist
was also a pioneer of evolutionary
epistemology and he made the statement
life is a cognitive process
um
so
if this is true and there's this
functional equivalence between the
mechanisms driving evolution learning
and science
then that implies that adaptation
uh or the genetic information that
corresponds to those physical
adaptations
are uh
equivalent
is equivalent to scientific knowledge
they're actually the same thing so
to kind of make this relationship clear
biological adaptation represents
knowledge of the environment and the
knowledge we acquire through learning
and science reflects adaptation to the
environment
so we see that there's no meaningful
distinction between adaptive information
and scientific knowledge both allow life
to predict an uncertain world control
matter constrain chaos and construct
order from this order
so the very same property that is
responsible for organic matter leaving
the planet in spaceships so this
anti-aggression uh is the same
uh property that allows organisms to
climb up hill
seemingly defying the force of gravity
of course uh the laws of physics aren't
violated in any way but uh
living systems are not uh constrained by
the laws of physics the way inanimate
systems are
so some examples a dolphin streamline
design which is a product of the
information stored in its genome
contains the knowledge of hydrodynamics
an eagle's wing design contains the
knowledge of aerodynamics not only can
we be certain that engineers see
knowledge in these functional structures
uh
there should be little doubt that they
inspired uh
our machines and and without that
information i don't think we would have
come to those
inventions at least not any time soon
um
camouflage
on an organism
represents knowledge of the environment
so
kind of bridging this idea of
evolutionary epistemology that evolution
builds up knowledge and that science is
an extension of the evolutionary process
making a bridge between that and
bayesian inference
uh requires this uh relationship between
adaptation and statistical correlation
so physicist carlo revelli which who has
gotten really interested in explaining
how this information
that underlies agency that behavior that
we see with living systems gets built up
through evolution uh
he wrote a great essay it
won the foundational questions institute
essay contest
um
a few years ago but um this work was
based on the work of david wolpert and
artem kolczynski artemy kolczynski and
basically
uh shows how this
adaptation builds up information in the
system that information
is really statistical correlation
between the organism and its environment
so
here's the simplest example it's a
bacterium performing chemotaxis
so bacteria so chemotaxis is basically
uh
a bacterium will uh swim in the
direction of food and swim away from
toxins so basically it's detecting this
chemical gradient that follows
um but
so we can see in this example
um and this isn't the case for all
species but you can imagine that a
bacterium that swings to the left when
nutrients are on the left
uh prospers compared to a bacterium that
swims at random
so
uh
with this
behavior where it's swimming towards
food
that is the product of a chance mutation
so it's in in some sense it's an
accident but when it discovers that
solution
that organism
is more likely to reproduce
so that solution
gets retained in the population it gets
sort of frozen hardwired in
and
so the process of adaptation is a
process that builds up a statistical
correlation between
the system the agent
and its environment
and so that
shared statistical correlation
represents mutual information so mutual
information is information that's shared
between the environment and the organism
and
uh just to explain that a little bit
more
uh this correlation
uh basically as this correlation gets
built up it's creating predictive
knowledge
so um
john maynard smith cites friedretzky who
did kind of the pioneering work applying
shannon's information theory to try to
quantify evolution
so dredsky argues that if some variable
a is correlated with the second variable
b then we can say that b carries
information about a for example if the
occurrence of rain is correlated with a
particular cloud then the type of cloud
tells us whether it would rain
so that's from a great essay called the
concept of information biology
so
we can see
that you have this little
rhyming equation here adaptation
equals statistical correlation equals
mutual information
uh and because that uh
shared information allows the organism
to predict its environment better
this process is also a process of model
optimization so the predictive model of
the organism
as it adapts starts to become more
accurate and so this whole process can
be seen
as a free energy minimization process
of course that's information theoretic
free energy it's the free energy of for
instance principle we're not talking
about thermodynamic free energy anyone
wants to ask a question or gets confused
about that
let me know
but it's basically uh those things are
related and it's something that's not
mentioned enough uh
minimizing information theoretic free
energy which is just
minimizing the prediction error of your
model
is what allows the organism to minimize
environmental free energy
so
by acquiring information reducing
your information theoretic free energy
allows
the organism to extract energy
and reduce
thermodynamic
free energy it minimizes the free energy
in the environment converts it into
entropy
so
we kind of see how this is getting into
universal bayesianism as it becomes more
correlated it gains information about
its niche and therefore becomes a better
predictor of that niche
um
so that's what adaptation is it's the
genome of the species accumulating
information that reduces the average
organism's uncertainty regarding the
environment
so um the genome is a knowledge
repository of solutions to environmental
challenges
that allows an organism with no brain
and no mind to anticipate events in the
environment so in this theory as i
mentioned before consciousness comes
later it comes with self-modeling
capacity
and a bacterium
would be kind of a zombie agent it would
have agency and it would move with
purpose
but that is not enough for mind or at
least mind
defined as consciousness
uh if you want to say that mind is just
information processing then yes there is
mind in these systems but that's
very different than saying that the
system has a subjective experience
and a first person perspective
that will come in the next talk but that
uh it's it's harder
so
that information stored in memory is
integrated into a statistical or
predictive model that determines the
causal control system's behavioral
repertoire or the full range of
behaviors an organism is capable of and
it is this mapping of sensory inputs to
motor outputs that makes the organism
move in ways that we normally associate
with mind or consciousness
um carl fursten in a great eon article
says all biological processes can be
construed as performing some form of
inference i think i already read that
but the free energy principle for those
aren't familiar
we've already explained it but the
bayesian brain hypothesis
and the free energy principle are the
same thing
uh the difference is that the free
energy principle applies to
all other adaptive systems where the
other one is just focusing on brains but
first and realize that this you know is
a model
and a process that
applies to any system that's trying to
resist the tendency towards disorder so
any system
to stay to continue persisting longer
than we would expect
uh naturally it must engage in bayesian
like learning to deal with environmental
uncertainty
how much time do i have left roughly
uh
still more than enough
okay keep going
um i'm definitely
more than half through i'd say i'm two
thirds of the way through
so uh john campbell has this great uh
paper called universal darwinism as a
process of bayesian inference that i
kept coming across
as i was trying to understand
uh non-equilibrium thermodynamics and
information theory um
yeah i should say actually
i should have gotten the books uh showed
you each book but um
there's a great book called the origin
and nature of life on earth by santa fe
institutes eric smith and harold
morowitz uh morowitz was a professor of
mine eric uh is a friend that uh we
would have these foundations of the mind
uh guild it was like a consciousness
club that would meet at the krasnow
institute where i got my phd
and um so their book the origin of life
on the origin of life in chapter eight
actually gets into this
information theory and uh this this
bayesian inference and describes the
origin of life and the evolution
of life as a
process of bayesian model selection
and so that was kind of what connected
non-equilibrium statistical mechanics to
these to this bayesian brain hypothesis
and i realized that you know these
theories were kind of
converging on the same ideas so john
campbell wrote this paper in 2016 he
says bayesian inference is an algorithm
for the accumulation of evidence-based
knowledge this algorithm is now seen to
operate over a wide range of
evolutionary processes including natural
selection the evolution of mental models
and cultural evolutionary processes
notably including science itself
so
uh when we say that evolution is a
process of bayesian model selection and
the book i mentioned with eric and
morowitz actually characterize evolution
as an inference engine
uh we're basically saying that when
organisms that aren't fit get weeded out
uh
that's basically models that aren't
predictive
getting eliminated so the organisms that
persist
are the models
that were able to predict the
environment best so inference and
prediction
are kind of the same thing uh since the
word inference is
a little obscure i guess um so
just to make this point a little more
clear
since nature is complex and
intrinsically unpredictable
uh
the model of an organism is at some
point guaranteed to fail when reality
surprises it
with the unexpected
so and that's what the free energy
principle is about minimizing surprise
is the same thing as minimizing
prediction error
so an organism gets eaten by a predator
a baby fails to reach his bottle a
scientific theory fails to explain new
data
um
basically when any of these things
happens it means that the model used to
predict reality is not completely
accurate
it contains a certain amount of
prediction error needs to be corrected
so what's the solution try something new
the old model worked well enough up to
that point so don't ditch it just vary
it a bit and see if it performs better
if it does not reduce surprise eliminate
that variant and try again if prediction
error is reduced replace the old model
with the new one so that it becomes the
reigning theory and the design template
for new variants to be based upon
when a model has been updated in this
way due to natural selection adaptive
learning or experimental testing we can
say that knowledge has been acquired and
environmental uncertainty reduced
so here we have an image um i should say
that uh infinity maps uh german software
mapping company uh helped me create
these images
uh oliver wanna i have to give a big
thanks to him
um this image has a little bit more
going on than i would want right now but
you could see that um
basically
this represents two
different mechanisms for learning
and adaptation so this one on the top
that we're going to talk about first is
the normal
uh competitive evolution sort of
darwinian survival of the fittest
while this mechanism over here is the
mechanism of self-organization
so let's first
talk about the normal
type of evolution we're familiar with
and show that
how this process of evolution that works
through variation and selection
actually uh
generates
predictive information and
creates a a model
which is
which
encodes knowledge
of the
biologically relevant
regularities in the environment so first
we have this
this is a
bacterium over here and so
this is the simplest model um you have
an organism that's an embodied theory or
a best guess about how to stay far from
equilibrium so
evolutionary epistemology sees organisms
themselves
as embodied theories so evolution is
basically
testing these different models
so
uh it basically reproduces and we know
that because there are going to be um
heirs in uh
in that process uh the genome will get
changed
uh
slightly and you will get
a generation
of progeny that all are slightly
different
they have slightly different
configurations
some of these configurations will be
better at extracting energy in
predicting the environment than others
and the ones that
aren't good at predicting the
environment they get filtered out by
natural selection
so here we see design four
is the winning design because it's the
best predictor and it's the best
predictor because it's the best
extractor of energy
and
so that uh design
uh
that that organism gets to reproduce and
then you have another generation
uh of designs that are slightly
different
and this process is an iterative process
just like science
and hypothesis testing so
um over generations
you will start to get uh designs that
are
better adapted to the
environment which we've explained means
that
they will be more correlated with the
environment
and being more correlated means being a
better predictor
um
so the knowledge that's left over after
this process is the adaptive information
stored in genetic material that reduces
environmental uncertainty and you see
that this process
will
ultimately lead to the evolution
towards the the best possible design so
it's it's an optimization a lot of
people don't think
that evolution is optimizing anything
there's been this you know kind of
philosophy that evolution does just good
enough
but we actually see that in terms of the
computation that it does to stay far
from equilibrium
that it's actually optimized for being
almost
maximally efficient with its use of
energy
it approaches something close to what's
called the land hour limit which david
wahlberg at sfi is written about
but uh
life is much more efficient uh with
computation in terms of energy
uh supply needed compared to all of our
technology so the human brain can do
uh solve problems that even our best
like ai systems can't solve and it does
so running on uh the equivalent of one
household light bulb
so we'll come back to this
self-organization
process
oh well actually we'll get into that
right now so
this is the normal uh process that we
think about when we think about
evolution generating
knowledge predictive knowledge
and so that's called phylogenetic
learning uh phylogenetic refers to these
like generations so
learning is generational the organisms
don't really learn because they don't
have brains they're not able to update
their model in real time so learning is
at the level of the population
and for learning to occur organisms have
to die before brains
basically you have to have this
uh competition uh
for there to be a learning process
however
there's also self-organization when
these organisms don't compete but
actually find a configuration find it
discover collective configuration
through their
somewhat random interactions with each
other
and when they find this collective
configuration through trial and error
basically the configurations that are
better at extracting energy will be the
ones
that are retained
um
so
donald campbell
father of evolutionary epistemology
uh explain this process this
evolutionary process
by which self-organization works as
blind variation and selective retention
or we can think of it as selection for
persistence or stability
so fitness kind of
there's a dawkins quote i think i come
out where richard dawkins said darwin's
uh
survival of the fittest is really
um
just a
more specific instance of a more general
law of survival of the stable
so when we think about
being fit
at the beginning we're talking about
just being uh stable being able to find
energy if you can't do that it doesn't
matter whether you have agents that
you're competing with or not because
if you can't get energy it doesn't
matter if there are other people
competing for it that you won't survive
so
you don't need replication
with variation
to evolve that's what this is this model
is saying
um and stuart kaufman from the santa fe
institute has
been talking about the importance of
this marriage between
darwinian evolution and
self-organization
but basically uh because there's not
this replication process
this is how evolution occurs so you have
a system
that's a collection of components parts
these parts can be molecules or they
could be
agents
and when
these molecules are pushed far from
equilibrium by a flow of energy of
course humans are eating food and
metabolizing energy so they're being
powered by energy flows as well
the system blindly explores various
configurations in the space of possible
designs via trial and error so this
system will move through a series of
configurations and those configurations
that allow the system to extract
sufficient energy to stay out of
equilibrium will get retained
while the configurations that don't
allow for energy extraction
will get filtered out either the system
will collapse and have to try a new
configuration
or it'll just revert to the the previous
stable
configuration and it will continue
trying to
explore that configuration space um
i should have said like here's a good
example like here's a depiction of this
configuration space we're talking about
life exploring the design space so
basically you have a
a designer configuration and then
uh
you get these uh different this
exploration of
different configurations that are
very close to the configuration you
started out with
so
you know i was thinking about giving a
talk on the origin of life but i
couldn't get into all this cool daisy
and stuff that's what the first part of
the book is about what's really
interesting is that we're finding that
self-organization
as mentioned is a darwinian process so
there's actually a name for this
dissipative adaptation and it shows that
this evolution towards these more stable
configurations dissipate more energy
when this happens at the level of
organisms that we're talking about it
shouldn't be surprising that
it dissipates more energy because
basically
as the organism evolves to be better at
extracting energy all that energy it's
extracting to maintain far from
equilibrium is being converted into
thermal entropy
so
all self-organizing processes are really
dissipative adaptation processes at
different levels so this process
philosophers would say is multiply
realizable so this process can happen at
different scales and that's exactly what
we see like
right here the same process so you would
have a society like exploring different
governance systems
and it doesn't know which government
system is going to work
the best beforehand it tries it
if it doesn't work well
like the fall of rome
um it will collapse and then it will
reassemble
so
just to wrap up the origin of life so we
have this process of dissipative
adaptation and
if it's being pushed by the flow of
energy
and it's doing this process here where
it's finding increasingly uh stable
configurations
collective configurations
then um
uh basically what will emerge is an auto
catalytic set we'll define that later
but basically
uh it's um
i'm using a lot of terms for philosophy
i was gonna say like
it's the beginning of an autopoetic
agent so like a self-maintaining agent
in its simplest form is a chemical
system that produces outputs
which are then
fed back into the system so that the
system
can uh self-amplify it's basically
creating
all of the molecules
uh that it needs to grow
and uh
it's thought that this process
you know occurred
the auto catalytic set is kind of the
precursor for the first cell so it's
kind of like a protocell
and um it was thought to occur uh around
hydrothermal vents which are under water
volcanoes
there's all this
energy flowing up from the the hot core
running through geochemical energy
and there's these rocky pores
in the rocks around hydrothermal vents
which
provide something like a a membrane like
a lipid
membrane to hold the components in a
mark off blankets so that the pores and
the rocks
were the mark off blanket for the
auto catalytic set and eric smith and
marwitz showed that
basically
feeding off inorganic inputs
like carbon molecules like not not
anything not organic chemistry where
it's like life but just like simple
like carbon hydrogen and oxygen feeding
off those
inputs um
basically the metabolic process uh it's
called the reverse krebs cycle so
uh that process
allowed uh
the first autocatalytic set to
continuously
self-amplify
um
through this through this process
so if this process is allowed to
continue
um further self-organization may
eventually lead to the emergence of an
organic computer that can process
integrate and store information about
the world so
what dissipative adaptation is doing
is uh as it's doing this blind variation
and selective retention process and it's
finding more stable configurations those
more stable configurations are also
predictive of the environment so this
dissipative adaptation process
is this auto catalytic set
modeling the surrounding energy
landscape so i'm arguing that this is
where modeling begins it even begins
before what we call life like rep
self-replicating life and it's
dissipative adaptation which is a
process
of modeling the the energy in the
environment
the energy sources
um
so
uh this isn't just one continuous
process there are these leaps
that are phase transitions basically
we've heard of phase transitions and
physics and chemistry uh
courses where you have like
water
being heated up and then transitioning
into a gas or the reverse when a gas
becomes frozen
uh you get a state of order that emerges
um
these uh transitions towards uh these
configurations that are good at
extracting energy
those uh have also been characterized
as phase transitions
so eric smith who i mentioned before
herald morwitz they have this phase
transition theory of life
which basically
uh
explains how um information gains
control
in these systems
um
and sarah walker and paul davies work on
this basically show that through this
process
of blind variation and selective
retention information gets built up in
this auto catalytic set and at some
point
there's what they call algorithmic
takeover
uh or informational control and the
system becomes an agent that can start
to
steer and control itself
in ways that wouldn't be predicted by
physics so
a living system is very much like we
didn't talk about dissipative structures
but like tornadoes whirlpools those
things emerge to dissipate an energy
gradient
uh
living things uh because of the process
of metabolism
we are this
cycling system this thermodynamic
energetic loop
um
uh but uh
what's it gonna say about that um
so yeah we are like the storm but we do
have control
over this storm we're a storm with
control so it doesn't really make sense
going back to sam harris's quote that
you are the storm you do not control it
it's literally the information that gets
built up through evolution
that allows
you know us being this dissipative
structure like a storm
to start controlling
its own behavior
um so the last part is just
an argument
for that second question why should
complexity increase
um
we know that this evolutionary process
where you build up this model
uh so we would think that this after
these generations of evolution this
organism is going to be well adapted to
its
environment but we know that adaptation
doesn't mean becoming more complex
always so sharks and crocodiles are
cited as species that haven't evolved
much at all
in many millions of years
cave fish actually
evolved to become more simple so
basically
fish with eyes got isolated and like an
underground environment where there was
no
uh need for sunlight and uh so
basically
um
fish
like
processing light like eyes didn't have
any survival advantage so
um
basically fish lost their eyes
uh over many generations of evolution
becoming simpler so if that's true why
should evolution increase complexity
the answer to that
it comes from this understanding that
evolutionary epistemology says that a
species adapting to a niche is like a
scientific theory being tested for
viability species will evolve not to
become increasingly complex but to match
the complexity of the environment
a sort of simplest solution to the
thermodynamic problem of staying far
from equilibrium so einstein famous we
said a theory should be
as simple as possible but no simpler
the same could be said about an organism
you want it to be
as simple as possible while it
accomplishes its task of extracting
energy it has to be complex enough
to be able to extract energy in a
competitive environment
but
a bacterium doesn't have to do it
doesn't need intelligence any extra
information processing higher level
cognition
would be energy wasted
um
that could
be energy that allows it to stay far
from equilibrium for longer and
replicate more so
it's not the case that everything will
evolve towards higher complexity
but
the reason that we do get
increasingly complex species over
evolutionary time in a way that i'm
saying is inevitable
so there is a progressive evolutionary
process that leads to higher forms
it has to do with uh niche emergence so
so basically
a species will evolve to become as
complex as its niche as its
environmental niche
but there will be increasingly complex
niches that emerge
for reasons that will be explained
but i will pause there
before i get to that which will be what
we end on
there are no other questions right now
so if anyone does have questions how
about they can feel free to ask it
during this last section give you a
second to
catch your breath and i know it's been a
ton of information like
my goal is that you know since this is
being recorded it'll be something that's
up um hopefully i've cited enough
literature that people can explore this
stuff themselves and see that like okay
it's not this guy that's like
uh claiming to have like a theory of
everything this isn't my theory
it's a synthesis that's emerging and um
uh really the story has been there for
quite some time and
the cybernetics pioneers actually a lot
of them were you could call them like
cosmic teleologists a lot of them did
see this continual increase in
complexity
of course there's nothing mystical about
it or supernatural about it
um
it's a mechanistic process
that doesn't change the fact that
nature seems to have these built-in
goals
that emerge from
the fundamental laws and constants the
parameters the the fine-tuning
but it's a completely natural
progressive teleological evolutionary
process
and so i'll just and you know this is
just
finishing up it's along the same line so
that's good the questions can come after
this and i know it's been quite a lot so
i will just try to
sum this up simply um
so uh
two important principles from
cybernetics
these came from ross ashby who also
created the principle of
self-organization which was really the
first time people took self-organization
seriously so
we think of complexity science as being
the science of self-organization but it
really goes back to cybernetics
um i think the term i think kant might
have talked about it but it was
ross ashby who tried to you know give it
a make it a principle and a formalized
concept
so there are these two concepts that
really i think
anybody interested in like coffers and
spacing brain hypothesis free energy
principle should be aware of because all
of the way he talks about like
evolution comes from this
ashby's work the good regulator theorem
it was also updated there there was the
internal model principle which came like
a decade later
good regulator theorem came
these both these laws i think came in
the 50s in the 40s or 50s and then i
think in the 70s the internal model
principle was created but it basically
says that any system that regulates or
controls another system must have a
model of that system
otherwise it can't regulate it so it
seems pretty obvious but
this talk of models kind of
starts here that is very familiar to
like anyone interested in like the free
energy principle
so
this
this can be applied to inanimate systems
i mean controllers are like house like
thermostats and stuff but ashby was
really interested in adaptive systems so
he was thinking about evolution so
applied to evolution
an organism must model its environment
uh if it's going to extract free energy
and an organism is a model of its niche
like a key is a model of the lock it
opens so when we talk about these models
it can be kind of extra kind of abstract
but
i think this
model
a key is a model of the lock it opens
really explains how an organism fits
into a niche
you could also say like a hand fits into
a glove but it really
the organism is a model of its
environment so natural selection is
essentially an information channel that
through evolution is pumping in
information
from the external world from the
environment into the organism such that
the organism
is
encoding the structure of reality and
encoding the structure of the world
and its design uh
include uh
uh encodes information about the outside
world
so it's kind of a
new way to think about evolution as this
process of
basically
the universe is modeling itself and
waking up through this process it's
pretty interesting um kind of
psychedelic
so um the law of requisite variety
is just telling you about the
sophistication of that model so how
complex does the model have to be for
the organism to stay far from
equilibrium
um ross ashby's law
says
so john naughton researcher at cambridge
uh kind of summed it up this way in
colloquial terms ashby's laws come to be
understood as a simple proposition if
the system is to be able to deal
successfully with the diversity of
challenges that its environment produces
then it needs to have a repertoire of
responses which is at least as nuanced
as the problems thrown up by the
environment so a viable system is one
that can handle the variability of its
environment or as ashby put it only
variety can absorb variety
so it's what we said before with
evolutionary epistemology
an organism
evolves to become as complex as its
environmental niche requires
it has to
specifically
have enough behavioral responses
which map onto internal states so it has
to have enough cognitive states
to
uh
respond to the number of challenges
that
the environment presents challenges
in its ability to extract energy
and when
when you get organisms and you get other
uh you get other agents other organisms
then
of course
what the organism has to model is much
more complicated because it doesn't have
to just model the energy source in its
environment like to get food it also has
to model other
modelers other cognitive agents
um
so yeah basically
any adaptive system has
a
uh
a behavioral repertoire and a repertoire
of accessible
mental states or for things without
brains computational states
and the number of states that the
organism can access
uh should match the number of challenges
the number of states
that could surprise the organism by the
environment
um so a cat must have at least as many
states as the ways the mouse can invade
it and the mouse has to have enough
behavioral states to get away
so they model each other
a swordsman like a fencer must have many
blocks as his opponent has attacks
and as we said
because bigger responses map onto unique
internal states
the loss of an organism must have as
many accessible states as required by
the complexity of niche
so we already said this uh organism is
some simplest solution to the
thermodynamic problem of seeing far from
equilibrium
so a well-adapted species represents a
biological solution to an existential
thermodynamic
dilemma it's a sort of living evolving
scientific theory about how to most
efficiently extract the free energy the
lifeblood of existence out of a
particular niche
some niches present a changing variety
of challenges that must be adapted to
you while others present hardly any at
all
so almost done here i know it's a lot um
hopefully this can kind of wrap up the
ideas and kind of show how they're all
connected um
but this is still on this question of
how complex
is the universe
uh how complex can it get so
olivia
olivia judson wrote this uh
published this paper called the energy
expansions of evolution it's really nice
people should check it out
uh so she says the history of the earth
life earth system can be divided into
five energetic epochs each featuring the
evolution of life forms that can exploit
a new source of energy these sources are
geochemical energy sunlight oxygen flesh
and fire
the first two are present at the start
but oxygen flushing fire all
consequences of evolutionary events
and then she makes this statement
by the way red is
quotes if
people haven't
uh figured that out so these are her
words i forgot to put quote marks um so
no category of energy source has
disappeared this has over time resulted
in an expanding realm of the sources of
energy available to living organisms and
a commitment
uh increase in the diversity and
complexity of ecosystems
so
here's the way to think about it um
so taking the thermodynamic perspective
and looking at organisms as energy flow
channels uh we can think of each niche
on earth as a sort of energy slot for a
given species and an evolving population
of organisms efficiently searching the
solution space will eventually just by
chance discover a solution to a
thermodynamic problem that it didn't
know existed
the discovery of a novel energy source
or energy extraction technique is both
how a new niche and a new species come
into existence
so phylogenetic learning which we saw in
that
chart
will naturally lead to speciation
because organisms will stumble upon new
ways to exploit thermodynamic niches
that were previously inaccessible to
life purely for design reasons we're
going to give examples on the next slide
so as the biosphere accumulates
knowledge through phylogenetic learning
not only is the solution space
corresponding to one kind of
thermodynamic problem being explored
there's a growing problem space each
with its own unique solution space
um
so in an evolution so there's an
evolutionary trajectory
that's not determined in the strict
sense
envisioned by laplace where like there's
no freedom in the future it's like set
in stone
but there is a sort of uh statistical
determinism what i've been calling a
non-equilibrium statistical determinism
that guarantees that basically the
inevitability of this emergence of a
distribution of far from equilibrium
attractors
of varying varying degrees of complexity
so each species can be seen as a an
attractor that's exploiting this niche
and you get this uh
basically this diversity where you have
uh
organisms uh exploiting like the the
energy
niches that were kind of the
easy ones to exploit on earth like the
geochemical free energy we mentioned
with the origin of life and then
sunlight was a
little bit of a more difficult challenge
to extract sunlight it took some time
for evolution to be able to do that
um
so uh extracting energy from the
hydrothermal vents uh source of energy
is really simple because the energy is
already like flowing through the system
it doesn't have to do much work to
extract sunlight you have you know a
moving
sun
it's a little bit more complicated but
not nearly as complicated as organisms
that eat other organisms so
heterotrophic organisms
because they will have to model not just
like a sun moving predictably through
the air but have to model all these
other agents
many of which are trying to eat them
to kill you um so
basically so answering this question why
increasingly intelligent species emerge
we started off with reductive autotrophs
those organisms around hydrothermal
vents they were a solution to the
problem of how to extract free energy
from geochemical gradients
um photosynthetic bacteria the ancestors
of plants for the solution to extract of
how to extract all the solar energy that
was flowing through the planetary system
so that was a big
discovery made by life is that you can
get energy directly from sunlight
heterotrophic organisms organisms that
eat other organisms where the solution
to the problem of how to extract energy
from life itself
once life starts having to model life
other agents with causal power and
adaptive behavior
the computational task of extracting
free energy gets increasingly difficult
as increasingly complex species arise
so by virtue of having to model each
other the complexity of some species
gets ratcheted up by what's known as an
evolutionary arms race
so
the lion is evolving you know lions are
producing offspring some of those lions
will be better at predicting the
gazelles movements the gazelle will also
be creating offspring and some of those
will be
better at predicting the lions attack
the ones that are better at predicting
are the ones that get to
uh stick around so you see how you have
this ratcheting mechanism that ratchets
that ratchet is
up complexity um
there's actually a principle called
the red queen principle
uh that says that for
an organism to simply stay in the game
of existence
certain organisms a certain species they
will have to become increasingly complex
and that comes from
uh alex in wonderland basically
there's a scene with the red queen and
alice's they're they're all running as
fast as they can and alice is like
you know i'm running fast as i i'm i
keep running but i'm i'm going nowhere
like so they're they're all running but
they're they're not making any distance
they're staying in place and the queen
says something like
oh you see here for that
uh
to go somewhere you'll have to run much
faster than that
um so
the idea is that
for a species
that has to deal with this complex
environment just to stay where it is
just to stay in the game of existence it
has to become increasingly complex it
has to keep adapting
so
one thing that i wanted to get into more
but i'm not going to
is this idea of empowerment it comes
from the computational neuroscience
literature
it's similar it comes from daniel palani
but it's very similar to
harvard's uh alex
wisner visner gross he has an idea
called causal and tropic forcing but
basically these people are arguing that
um
well
visitor growth is arguing that a causal
entropic force
uh means that like basically with like
evolution you'll get a system systems
that uh
are trying to maximize
the number
of states they can respond to so the
maximize
and
the number of states they can respond to
is mirrored by their internal diversity
so systems naturally try to increase the
number of states
and it's this
ability that allows for intelligence
because if you have more states going
back to this law of requisite variety
you can respond to more challenges
so
not every species is increasing
empowerment
but you will get the emergence of
increasing
uh increasingly complex
species because uh each species
serves as food
for a potential new species um
you will get increasingly complex
species that emerge over time
and they will be increasingly empowered
meaning that they can respond
to more environmental states and that
they have more accessible
mental or cognitive states
um i explained some of this
in the last
slide but i'll just explain a little
more so open-ended niche emergence why
is the evolutionary record shown a trend
of the emergence of increasingly complex
forms
um
because when all conceivable niches on
earth were filled that wasn't the end
new species created new niches because
the free energy spot they provide is
themselves their food
so
cybernetics guy he's kind of like the
last
living
cyberneticist kind of um i'm sure there
are other people that call themselves
that but he's kind of kept that title
even when it like
wasn't trendy
um he says it is well documented by
evolutionary biologists that ecosystems
tend to become more complex the number
of different species increases and the
number of dependencies and other
linkages linkages between species
increases
he cites eo wilson who recently passed
away
um
who did a lot of work that that kind of
inspired a lot of the
concepts in the book um
not just this niche emergence but also
talking about super organisms so
collectives like ant colonies
self-organizing systems that all scales
but he said not only do ecosystems
contain typically lots of niches that
will eventually be filled by new species
but there is a self-reinforcing tendency
to create new niches
what does that mean
it means uh the biosphere
certainly ecosystems are themselves auto
catalytic sets
so
seth lloyd he's talking about these
chemical auto catalytic sets but it's i
should have had this on the earlier
slide but it'll be a good way to
kind of show the equivalence between
ecosystems
cethloid says auto catalytic sets of
reactions are powerful systems in
addition to computing they can produce a
wide variety of chemical outputs in
effect an auto catalytic set of
reactions is like a tiny computer
controlled factory for producing
chemicals
some of these chemicals are the
constituents of life
now stuart kaufman
big you know
one of the main names who's kind of this
whole talk he's kind of put these ideas
out there
uh since like the early 90s well
actually going back farther than that
but he started writing books in the 90s
and really gaining exposure for the
santa fe institute
he's written a recent paper well
semi-recent
about
niche emergence as an auto catalytic
process so ecosystems are auto catalytic
auto catalytically closed
self-sustaining reaction networks so
they're auto poetic agents
that reliably drive up biological
diversity and complexity as they self
amplify and evolve
so when you think about it really all
integrated networks of adaptive systems
functions out of auto catalytic sets
there's been a lot of papers showing
this economies
in a sense are autocad sets including
the social organisms we call societies
or civilizations
so these networks are common because
they emerge spontaneously when many
organisms repeatedly interact with one
another and discover synergistic
collective configurations
as nature often pressures them to do
so we're at the end um almost
uh we've explained why complexity
increases
evolution will not increase the
complexity of every species they will
become adapted to their niche they will
match the complexity of the niche
however because new niches are always
emerging because species act as food for
a potential new species
um
because of that process you will get
this increase uh you will get species
that emerge that have a higher number
of uh a larger repertoire of mental and
behavioral states so the law of
requisite variety really explains why
more complex environments create more
complex niches and this is open-ended
there's really no
uh
limit
to how far this process can go
especially since humans
who are the pinnacle of this process
we're not
you know a lot of people have been
against
these kinds of views because it seems
like it's saying that humans are
superior
we're superior maybe computationally but
not superior in any other sense we're
actually part of the biosphere which is
this integrated interconnected system
so
it's really you know it doesn't make
sense to think of us as like superior to
nature because the whole biosphere is an
organism that we're just sort of an
organ for
uh we're basically the nervous system
of the planet the cybernetic
uh global system that people have called
gaia some people don't like that name i
think it's a perfectly good name
but um
that's why uh complexity gets ratcheted
up but the final
um
uh i guess uh part of this complexity
increase story
is that not only do you get increasingly
complex species
uh those species will interact
naturally to form
higher level
uh
adaptive systems which are collectives
so um
i call this the principle of recursive
self-organization based on ashby's
principle of self-organization
what i'm arguing is that when you have a
biosphere with these agents and you have
some are simple and some are complex
naturally those agents will interact
when they interact
they will
in many cases discover
synergistic collective configurations so
configurations that make it easier for
each agent to extract the energy they
need to stay far from equilibrium
so
why do interacting agents link up to
form stable holes for the exact same
reason that molecules with the right
chemical diversity will form stable auto
catalytic reaction sets when pushed by a
flow of energy
working collectively allows the whole
system to extract more free energy with
less work
we can that's the whole point of synergy
is that working together
makes your workload easier because
there's a distribution of labor
and it's it's really nice um that you
know this
uh
distribution of species with some simple
and some complex
uh that's really what you need to create
this like uh cybernetic adaptive system
at the level of a planet because a
system uh needs diversity among its
components in structure and function for
there to be this distribution of labor
labor which makes it this
uh
collective whole this synergistic uh
holistic unit um
so
it's actually good
that evolution in adaptation isn't
increasing this the complexity of each
species
like each species isn't becoming
intelligent like roaches aren't becoming
like more and more intelligent over time
with no limit um the biosphere wouldn't
be stable if that were the case uh it's
really uh ecosystems need this diversity
among components
just as a car
with made of all engines isn't going to
be functional or
our organism made of all brains you need
a variety of parts some simple some
complex because they all do different
functions
um so nature promotes cooperation
collaboration and synergy because it is
thermodynamically beneficial for all
parties
synergistic collective configurations
will eventually be discovered by many
component systems that are exploring
various states or configurations through
the blind variation and selective
retention mechanism mentioned
organisms only compete until they
finally figure out what that working
together makes everyone's task easier
and that goes for humans too so it's
kind of a moral lesson for
everybody the nations have to work
together
we shouldn't um
get rid of the nations there shouldn't
just be this evolution into this like
global government because the nations
are actually
uh provide this diversity that we're
saying is important uh because you need
this uh diversity of component parts to
create a division of labor
so
there's strength in diversity this is
different than the evolutionary picture
of survival of the fittest whereas
there's like this idea that the stronger
the most intelligent survive this is
saying that that's not true it's the
most adaptive that survive has nothing
to do with strength or intelligence
sloths have been around for many
millions of years despite
being sloths being slow because they
exploit a source of free energy that's
not being
exploited by another
uh species so
um
going back to this kind of global
message you want nations to retain their
identities but you also want them at the
same time to come together
and to
work synergistically so
you basically want something like a
global system but
this
there has to be the optimal balance
between centralization and
decentralization
um
neither
approach will be good on its own there
needs to be this balance
so
um
as long as the biosphere is creating a
growing variety of complex adaptive
systems some of those will interact to
produce higher level complex adaptive
systems which will come together to form
even larger ones
this process continues
uh at higher scales so
i didn't go into this uh left out a kind
of a neat picture that
shows a brain and then the planet and
it's like information networks but
uh i do i i hope that you know talk
about gaia and global brain will become
uh will be taken as seriously as it
should be
uh they really only weren't taken
seriously because there were mystical
notions associated with this word gaia
which wasn't even james uh
lovelock's
uh fault he act the name guy came from
his neighbor
who is actually the author of lord of
the flies
william golding so
blame him for the for the flowery
metaphor with gaia um
but yeah the the biosphere is a
cybernetic organism and we are forming
something like the global brain
and a self-replicating biosphere
uh
is essentially
the next step and when we are trying to
terraform
planets like mars that can be seen as
the biosphere replicating
uh
for humans to
at this point in our stage of
development
we would have to kind of convert mars to
like
something like a biosphere to have like
oxygen and so you can see how it's
replication with variation
you get the same sort of thing but
because it's a different planet there's
going to be
a variation it's not going to be exactly
the same but that's how the evolutionary
process continues
i should have showed this earlier this
is just showing how like
eukaryotic
single-celled organisms like amoebas
will come together to form communities
like a slime mold
these
multicellular organisms
come together to form colonies you see
this
ant colony ants actually really do form
a super organism you can see here they
actually build a bridge out of their
bodies so that some ants can like climb
across that bridge so
it really makes sense to call it a super
organism or at least like a super
adaptive system or like a meta
meta system um
because without it we can't make sense
of this collective behavior that's
functional um of course human
civilization we again see this hierarchy
now it makes more sense
uh we see that these evolutionary
transitions oh yeah these are called
evolutionary transitions
sometimes i use the name meta-system
transition because
um
if we were talking about the brain i
would also talk about like uh the
emergence of a prefrontal cortex which
is like a high level controller um
that's also like a meta system
transition so meta system transitions
are a little
extendous where it's not talking
necessarily about evolutionary
transitions but these other transitions
where
systems
start to model themselves
um so here we see uh
how
evolution has created these
different memory
systems these knowledge repositories
so it's that
process of recursive self-organization
creates new memory systems when you get
go from single cell life to
multi-cellular life to life with brains
uh it's uh these are in revolutions in
information storage machinery
so you can see how the information in
the biosphere gets accumulated
through an evolutionary process
um
these
are the final points
yeah so knowledge is powers not just the
hollow buzz phrase of the digital age
it's true in the most fundamental way
uncertainty reducing information is
life's first and last weapon in ongoing
war with disorder
without knowledge life cannot exist for
more than a moment much less colonize
the galaxy and beyond
this suggests that setting out on the
path toward cosmic superiority is not a
choice that intelligent agents like homo
sapiens make upon careful reflection nor
is it just some quirky ambition we
stumbled onto by chance
this is the main point humanity's
collective desire to transcend mortality
and expand outward into space so
apparent from our
current scientific and technological
endeavors spacex
uh this doesn't emerge as an accident
this is inevitable consequence of the
fact that continual knowledge
acquisition
is a fundamental biological imperative
if life wants to persist
and stay far from equilibrium at some
point it has to get off the planet
because the sun
is
going to die and uh it's these sorts of
problems these existential problems
which uh create progress because it's
our awareness of this problem
which uh
forces us to
uh search the configuration space for
the solutions that solve the problem so
as natural selection pumps information
from the inanimate world into life
nature begins modeling itself encoding
its own structure and the universe
begins to wake up
where the cosmos come alive not
metaphorically but literally
this is ray kurzweil's uh image from his
book the singularity is near
you can see that
he sees this he calls this the
the the destiny of of life in the
universe and he's not shy about using
that word
um again it's not determined in a strict
sense of replace this
uh kind of a statistical determinism
that creates these
uh series of attractors
and um
you've seen famous people uh
so you know some people see that idea
and they'll have been reading brian
green and listening to all these
reductionists and think that's not a
scientific view
well uh
that's not true and um
i hope to see more of these people
speaking out about it so christoph coke
in
confessions of a romantic reductionist
says the rise of sentient life within
times wide circuit was inevitable
teohara deschard in who really came up
with this don't have time to talk about
him french philosopher and jesuit you
should look into
is correct in his view that the islands
within the universe if not the whole
cosmos are evolving toward ever greater
complexity and self-knowledge to be
clear he's not saying that earth had to
bear life that
you know
primates had to walk the african glass
lands
but he says i do believe that the laws
of physics overwhelmingly favored the
emergence of consciousness the universe
is a work in progress such a belief
evokes
jeremiah i don't know the same word for
many biologists and philosophers but the
evidence from cosmology biology and
history is compelling
so there's some uh
advanced blurbs for this book uh if you
want to pre-order it
um it comes out in june uh but every uh
order that i get from now until then
will count towards my first week sales
total so that will help me get on
bestsellers list
if you want to program it now and you
email me um i will send you a copy soon
of this novel i also wrote called road
to omega i was pretty busy in the last
five years
yeah i went into a cave for like four or
five years but this
uh it's a vehicle for the science and
phosphate about kind of like an
anti-iron rand at this shrug maybe the
opposite phosphate um and the road to
omega sub stack kind of turns his
philosophy into kind of an effort to
um
save the world with uh science
epistemology and blockchain technology
uh blockchains are part of this
self-organization process
and that's the longest talk i've ever
given
that's the longest i ever talked at one
time probably my wife will probably say
that's not true but
i'm tired so let's
open it up to questions and thank you
for your immense patience
it's awesome to hear and
think about it
so there are two questions in the chat
first is from dean
dean asks
how would we explain caring through a
lens of free will or no free will would
free will deniers say there is no caring
when it appears that agents can or do
fully care
yeah so great question
unfortunately i don't have much to say
without
saying the things that i was going to
bring up in the next talk really
explaining what free will is i guess i
should just say right now uh kind of a
brief explanation of what i mean by free
will so i've i hope i've made the
argument that agency emerges
uh in
adaptive systems that start off as
biological organisms
and um to the person itself driving car
thing i uh uh just to mention that real
quick i don't think they're agents but i
do think uh
it's possible to create systems with
agency
um for reasons that i haven't gone into
um
uh it seems important that the systems
have a certain type of architecture so
not like a standard computer as a von
neumann architecture and it's not uh
distributed or integrated in the way the
brain is
so it's not integrating much information
so these systems won't have causal power
they won't be agents um
so
neuromorphic hardware has been a lot of
people think that's going to allow
machines that can
think and perhaps even be conscious um i
think maybe that's the way to go
uh it's probably a lot more complicated
than that it's a step in the right
direction
so agency is real it's uh due to
information gaining causal power in a
system and starts
uh
it starts
steering the system so
you'll see like a bacterium performing
chemotaxis but does it make sense to say
that the bacterium has free will when
it's going this way in that just because
it's not predictable in the way an
inanimate system is
so i would say that they have agency but
they don't have free will
what
uh free will is and it's not my idea
other people have kind of been talking
in this way kevin mitchell uh has a book
neurogeneticist uh
he's coming out with a book called
agents which is all about agency and
free will but um the idea is that
we are agents with causal power
but um we're sort of uh
where
um our responses like are basically uh
programmed responses uh that are
responses that occur
um
automatically uh that are informed by
this uh information that's been built up
through evolution and adaptive learning
so a lot of the time we go through the
day and we're not really thinking about
things like
driving or like waking up and like
you know going to the fridge we're not
putting conscious thought into that so
that wouldn't seem to be
free will
to me you're you're kind of acting on
autopilot so what free will is is a
higher level of control that emerges
with something like a prefrontal cortex
in a global workspace basically free
will allow a prefrontal cortex allows an
agent
to override its uh instinctive and
automatic behaviors
and so
free will is something that uh
that we have but only if we're
exercising this higher level of control
it's associated with cognitive control
or executive control effort full control
and basically
um
if you have a healthy functioning
prefrontal cortex
uh
you're going to basically the conscious
mind is monitoring
uh consciousness is a monitor uh so it's
it's monitoring uh your uh behaviors and
if it uh
detects that there's some optimal
behavior for whatever reason like it's
just automatic kind of instinctual let's
say someone says something that
makes us angry
and we respond immediately with like
pushing them or something uh that's not
a wise
uh move and that maybe may happen when
we're fearful
because of the amygdala response and we
just have this automatic behavior
um but uh free will would be when uh the
conscious mind
overrides that process
and uh
the bet actually the free will studies
that everybody cites as saying that we
don't have free will
he actually never said that he said free
will is in this veto power like maybe
some of our voluntary movements occur
without conscious thought
but it's our ability to override those
movements uh that is the source of free
will
but there was more problems with that
actually um the studies have
coked at a study showing that
uh basically
um
that free will um
uh
readiness potential which is like a
spike in electrical activity that occurs
before you do this voluntary movement
this movement you think is voluntary
and everyone thought that this meant
that you're not really making a
conscious decision that you could see
this spike in brain activity earlier
than the person thought they made the
voluntary voluntary decision
but a new study has shown that that's
only the case when we're making like
arbitrary decisions and when they had
people making a decision about
when when to donate like a large amount
of money to a charity you actually saw
this readiness potential disappear
and so it seems like deliberate thinking
which is still this like prefrontal
cortex
and there's this distinction between
access consciousness and phenomenal
consciousness that i didn't go into that
i would in the next talk that adam
saffron and integrated world modeling
theory really gets at
but the idea is that the prefrontal
cortex does allow us to override
automatic behaviors and that is a sort
of freedom
that we have and we also lose it
uh in cases of schizophrenia you see
impaired
uh prefrontal cortex activity and drug
addicts you see impaired activity
in drug addicts you see
they do repetitive behavior even when
they know that it's
uh
not beneficial to them they will still
engage in that so they're kind of stuck
in this loop for this unhealthy
attractor
with schizophrenia there's patients that
report being pushed around by
forces that are beyond their control
i think that's because when the
prefrontal cortex is uh
basically deactivated um
people lose this sense this ability to
override their automatic behaviors
and i think that's what those people are
experiencing this sort of loss of this
higher level agency that we've called
free will um
another interesting just the final
interesting thing to mention about that
is uh cotard's syndrome cotard's
delusion is this delusion where people
think they're dead they think they're um
like ghost or just not alive it's really
weird a lot of people die from
starvation because they think they don't
have to eat because they think they're
already dead
um you actually see from narrow imaging
studies they've showed uh
like impaired activity in the prefrontal
cortex so maybe these people who think
they're dead
have lost this high level agency and and
they feel like they're ghosts or
something um
as far as caring
uh
so um caring is a part of like
emerge through evolution because you do
have this benefit to cooperating with
each other this self-organization
process that we talked about that
happens naturally because
basically you find that when you work
together you minimize conflict and
align it you align interest
and so caring altruism empathy all of
those things are as natural
uh and as darwinian as anything else but
you have to
add on to evolutionary theory all of
this stuff about self-organization and
cooperative evolution
um
as far as you see he said something
about why people
uh who uh
don't believe in free will i forget the
exact point about the caring what was
that um when
when it appears that agents can or do
fully care
sorry what was that what was the first
part of it
um how would you explain caring through
a lens a free will or no free will would
free will deniers say there is no caring
when it appears that agents can or do
fully care
yeah no it's it it flies in the face of
like uh our our everyday experience so
like
yeah um
i
the
the the amount of contradictions and
like logic that doesn't make sense when
you go down that path of there being no
free will or agency
you just
you just get into absurd territory it's
i think when we look back it's gonna
look quaint
that for so long that we thought that
everything was determined in this strict
sense
and it's really a big issue because
these people who believe that if they
believe it if they take it to heart
they're experiencing cognitive
dissonance at every moment you know and
the people who
argue against agency
they talk about religious people having
to compartmentalize
to deal with you know the the real world
but anybody who believes that we don't
have agency has to compartmentalize in
the same way
uh funny little conversation between sam
harris and his uh wife um
uh annika harris uh who wrote a book
called conscious that is a great
accessible book but it leaves out like
everything that i've discussed and that
i would discuss about like
the bayesian brain hypothesis
uh global workspace theory doesn't
really go into integrated information
theory in any depth so like all of the
things that they're missing
that do explain a lot of this stuff uh
can be found in like modern neural
science so we are making a lot of
progress
towards
you know understanding the hard problem
of consciousness so subjective
experience but also a free will and
agency
but it's funny because they're having
this conversation in the podcast
and they're discussing whether since
a belief and no free will as mentioned
that new york times article
i think 2011 showed that
they have less moral behavior and it can
you know cause depression they're
discussing whether they should tell
their daughter about free will or not
that she doesn't have any free will the
discussion is like should we tell our
daughter that she doesn't have free will
but the actual discussion
implies that they believe that they have
some choice whether to tell her or not
they're having a discussion about
whether they should do this or not so
there's a contradiction in their
conversation
that contradicts what they believe
what's interesting is that
if they do tell her that she has no free
will and she believes it she's actually
gonna
have negative mental effects like it
will
you know be harmful um assuming that she
really believes it i don't know if it
has that in everyone but
you do see studies that show that um so
if we do have free will it's a very
bad thing to be telling people
um
and the last thing i'll say about that
is
well it's it's interesting because
if she's familiar with epistemology and
they tell her that she doesn't have free
will but she goes okay that's based on a
model that has uncertainty and that
model may be disproved
then she
might not have the negative effects of
free will so i think everyone should
practice being a good bayesian and
understand that our models our theories
even the one that i just talked about um
will have errors and will be shown to be
wrong and
if reductionists do that they won't call
free will belief and free will like
comparing them to horoscopes which is
just i think a horrible statement and
kind of funny that physicists don't like
it when like neuroscientists start and
biologists start like talking about
physics
it's kind of strange that physicists are
are so sure that we don't have free will
when they're not familiar at all with
the neuroscience
behind agency and free will
so
would you like me to
just read a comment in the chat
otherwise i think we can kind of come to
a close
um if there's anything yeah i can do one
more question yeah well uh marco and
dave and others thanks a lot for the
great
comments and commentary in the chat i
hope that bobby i have you check the um
live chat replay
um and uh sean o'connor wrote thanks for
the good and informative talk
dr azarian mentioned the idea of
evolutionary arms race i was hoping to
recommend that he consider if he hasn't
how an intra-specific evolutionary arms
race may relate
i'm not familiar with the specific so uh
perhaps like a game theory
red queen not between uh two species but
within one
[Music]
species
yes
so
you would have an evolutionary arms race
there too yeah certainly because you're
competing with other organisms um
and uh
uh john maynard smith who i mentioned
earlier uh talking about like this
causal power of information and biology
he uh
was the person to bring von neumann's
game theory to biological evolution
so he did uh he basically
showed that there is this you know game
theory sort of process being played out
i think he
his examples use different species
but i think within species um
you would see the sorts same sort of
thing of course if it's not humans you
know if you have other
species people are competing
organisms are competing you will get
increased complexity but there are
limits so just because there's these
evolutionary arm races
uh within and between species
there will still be a limit because
uh
they have to model the environment and
just modeling all these unnecessary
variables
uh is is wasteful so
um
it will ratchet up complexity
in species but
um
i think at least with the planet earth
and our biosphere
that uh
that humans are this sort of leading
envelope
uh of complexity and um so it really
just is open-ended with the most complex
species so the most complex species is
the one that will evolve toward higher
complexity
and uh
really there might be a limit there
there are reasons to think there are
limits to how far human biological
intelligence can emerge there's i mean
can evolve towards there's something
called a cephalization limit which is
like how big our brain can get because
of reasons like having to do with like
the skull
and
um
so
but what's interesting is
part of this process
this evolutionary process is popper and
newer people like dennett have mentioned
continues with science and culture and
technology
so humans really have open-ended
complexity because we're uh we're
augmenting ourselves with technology so
while biology biological complexity may
have limits there's no limits
once we start merging with our
technology
and we shouldn't see technology
as separate from
life
it's an extension of biology so the
extended phenotype richard falcons
explains like beaver dams considers like
the dam that the beaver instinctually
builds as part of the whole phenotype so
the ecosystem the organism there's
really no clear division between the
organism and the ecosystem and david
chalmers has the extended mind
hypothesis which says that our phones
are extensions of our minds
and um
all of our devices are and
for that reason we need to be worried
about privacy but we also need to not be
scared of technology we just need to use
technology to become more human so we're
not transcending
like humanity and biology
technology will allow us to become hyper
biological
very
interesting note perhaps to close it on
anytime you want the dot too
we can make it happen it can be any
format we can invite anyone else on
um
really
awesome and interesting to think about
do you want any last words
um if if i come back to talk about free
one agency it'd be great to have like
kevin mitchell or um maybe aircoil who's
done a lot of work on uh top-down
causation and causal emergence that was
really influenced uh influential on the
book
um i think if you know
people you can um twitter tag them or
email us and uh email them and cc us or
just contact us and we'll do that on our
site
thanks been super fun thanks daniel
really appreciate it great appreciate
you reading a draft of the manuscript
just like in a few days to give me some
feedback that actually helps their
little mistakes
in the book um
i heard you mention marco thanks uh to
marco and anybody else who's uh been
watching and
chiming in with questions really
appreciate it sorry for the information
overload
maybe watch this again
maybe micro dose
or um
maybe some legal stuff delta eight or
keep stay hydrated